<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>Atomic Musings</title>
		<link>http://atomicblom.github.io/</link>
		<description>Atomic units of thought</description>
		<copyright>2016</copyright>
		<pubDate>Fri, 05 Aug 2016 12:21:52 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Fri, 05 Aug 2016 12:21:52 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Hello Dynamics World</title>
			<link>http://atomicblom.github.io/posts/hello-dynamics-world</link>
			<description>&lt;p&gt;Over the last month and a bit or so at my work, I've been working on replacing a legacy system with Dynamics CRM.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
			<guid>http://atomicblom.github.io/posts/hello-dynamics-world</guid>
			<pubDate>Sun, 08 May 2016 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
			<content:encoded>
                                        


&lt;p&gt;Over the last month and a bit or so at my work, I've been working on replacing a legacy system with Dynamics CRM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm optimistic that Regardless of how people feel about it, I think it will be a good fit for the system it's replacing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Straight out of the gate however, there are a number of things that worried me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, the plugin code that I had been given had no tests, everything was static methods with raw linq-to-crm, so it wasn't even designed with testing in mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, the front end, a BA had written a bunch of JavaScript to add some nice features, but the JavaScript was potentially quite buggy in the way it was implemented.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, I was entering the Dynamics scene with no training, and the knowledge that people have done a lot with Dynamics, but it's also really easy to screw it up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that in mind, I'd like to start a series of blog posts about how I reengineered our plugins with the following goals in mind:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The plugins should be unit testable&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The plugins should use IoC framework so that they only contain what they need to function.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The plugins should provide insight into how they're functioning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile on the frontend, I've set up a WebPack workflow to allow us to write ES6/7 JavaScript using Async/Await to improve the readability and durabiliy of the JavaScript.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is my hope that my Blog will help others to write better code and provide a place where people can offer me advice to how I can improve our workflow as well.&lt;/p&gt;




                                </content:encoded>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>